Hey, Sein!
喂，贊恩！
That mage is willing to take a photo of us.
那個魔法使想幫我們拍張照片喔
A photo?
照片？
What are you talking about?
你在說什麼啊？
Come on, let's go!
好了啦，走吧！
This is going to be the beginning of our legend!
我們的傳說就從那張照片開始！
ORIGINAL STORY BY KANEHITO YAMADA / TSUKASA ABE
（原作：山田鐘人，作畫：阿部司）
29 YEARS FROM THE DEATH OF HIMMEL THE HERO
（勇者欣梅爾逝世的29年後）
KLAR REGION IN THE NORTHERN LANDS
（北方諸國，庫拉地區）
Is this warrior you mentioned really strong?
妳說的那位戰士真的這麼強嗎？
He's a dwarf who's been protecting this village for almost 400 years.
他可是守護了這個村子 將近四百年的矮人啊
How long do dwarves usually live for?
矮人族一般能活多久？
About 300 years.
大概三百年左右
People call him Old Man Voll.
大家都叫他弗爾爺爺
He's my long-lived friend.
他是我一位長壽的朋友
I wanted to have a chat with him before he dies.
我一直都想在他去世前 好好跟他敘個舊
What's sad is that it's not a joke.
這種話可不能亂說
But it's true that
但說真的
there aren't many people who can talk about the past
能夠跟芙莉蓮大人敘敘舊的人
with Mistress Frieren.
確實是沒有幾個
It's nice to make stops like this on our journey once in a while.
旅途中偶爾這樣逗留一會也不錯
Maybe I'll stay for about ten years?
要不要逗留個十年呢？
No more than one week.
只可以待一星期喔
That's the village, huh?
就是那個村子吧？
Old Man Voll.
弗爾爺爺
Long time no see.
好久不見了呢
Look. Isn't he so cool, looking like a seasoned old warrior?
怎麼樣？看起來 身經百戰的老戰士很帥吧？
He's still considered a warrior?
他還自認為是戰士嗎？
Who are you again?
妳是哪位啊？
He's just a frail old man.
都已經是個老糊塗了
I'm Frieren.
我是芙莉蓮喔
That's right…
是呢
You're still pretending to be senile?
你還要裝傻到什麼時候？
Many people die during battle because they let their guard down.
戰場的死因絕大多數是因為大意
It is the most effective tactic against both demons and mankind.
不管對手是魔族還是人類 這招都是最有效的戰術
You can't get up, can you?
站不起來吧？
No matter how experienced a warrior is,
不管一名戰士經驗有多豐富
if they lower their defense,
一旦降低防備心的話
they can easily suffer fatal injuries.
隨隨便便都能受到致命傷
If I had unsheathed my blade,
如果老夫剛剛是拔劍出擊
you would've lost your legs.
你的腿就已經不在了
I see you still use cowardly tactics.
你還是老樣子 用這種卑鄙的方式戰鬥呢
Frieren,
芙莉蓮
I welcome you. Make yourself at home.
歡迎妳來，把這裡當自己家吧
Wait, Frieren.
等等，芙莉蓮
I can't walk.
我站不起來啊
Stark, have him train you while you're there.
修塔爾克，既然到了這裡 就讓他好好鍛練你一番
Yes…
是…
What a terrifying old man.
真是不得了的老爺爺呢
Please use these logs for firewood.
請用這些木頭來生火吧
Hey, we want to stay for ten years, so can you find us a job?
我們打算待個十年 能幫我們找工作嗎？
Mistress Frieren, we are staying no more than one week.
芙莉蓮大人，只能待一星期喔
All right, fine.
知道了啦
We're such a small village…
我們村子很小
There was no one to accept my request, so I'm really grateful.
所以都沒有人接受我的委託 真是太感謝了
We have nothing to do anyway.
反正我們也無事可做
My goodness,
話說回來
I can't believe Old Man Voll had a friend.
弗爾爺爺竟然會有朋友
I've never seen him talk so enthusiastically.
我從來沒見過他聊天聊得那麼開心呢
He's so senile that we can't even hold a conversation.
他年紀實在太大了 平常連正常的對話都無法進行
He's been protecting this village from monsters and demons for ages,
從很久以前開始，他就一直 保護這個村子不受魔物跟魔族侵擾
but we don't even know why.
但原因是什麼，無人知曉
He's like a guardian deity.
他就像守護神的角色一樣
He's always been alone, huh?
一直以來，他一定很孤獨吧
One week just flew by.
一星期轉眼就過去了
How is Stark?
修塔爾克怎麼樣了？
Humans learn so fast.
人類的成長還真快啊
He's improved quite a bit.
多少有點進步了
Oh yeah?
是嗎？
It's been fun, Old Man Voll.
真是愉快的時光，弗爾爺爺
I'm really grateful to you, you know.
到現在我都還是很感激你喔
You gave me
因為弗爾爺爺
the opportunity to get to know Himmel and everyone.
給了我了解欣梅爾他們的機會
Old Man Voll, why are you protecting this village?
弗爾爺爺 您為什麼要一直守護這個村子呢？
It's all in the past.
那已經是很久以前的事了
It doesn't matter anymore.
理由是什麼也不重要了
People don't risk their lives for things that "don't matter."
誰都不會為了不重要的事情拚上性命
I am only
老夫只是
protecting the village
在守護愛妻
that my wife loved.
最愛的村子
She was a human.
她是個人類
All I am doing is fulfilling a promise
老夫所做的一切只是為了守住
that I made long ago.
很久以前許下的承諾
But I don't intend to talk about it in detail.
但這件事我不想再多說了
There's no way
我再也無法將那個人的
I can accurately describe her face, voice, or gaze anyway.
相貌、聲音，甚至是眼神 準確地描述出來
These memories are for me alone.
這些是只屬於老夫的回憶
It must sound silly that I have been keeping a promise
聽起來很愚蠢吧，老夫竟然一直
I made with someone who is already dead.
守著與逝者之間的承諾
It may.
是這樣呢
But I'm sure that person
但我相信那個人
is happy to know that you are keeping
要是知道您信守承諾的話
your promise.
一定會感到很高興
Himmel, you are a good hero.
欣梅爾，你是很好的勇者
I'm sure you will defeat the Demon King.
我相信你一定能打敗魔王
My wife was also yearning to live in an era of peace
老夫的妻子也一直期望著 能夠活在不再有魔王的
where there is no Demon King.
和平時代來臨的日子
The great hero named Himmel will live inside my memory,
名為欣梅爾的偉大勇者 會活在我的回憶裡
and I will carry it into the future.
而我會將這份回憶帶到未來
That's very nice of you,
真的很感謝您的好意
but you don't have to go that far.
但是您不需要做到這個地步
I have Frieren and Eisen in my party.
我的隊伍裡已經有芙莉蓮跟艾冉了
I won't live as long as an elf.
我可沒有精靈族那麼長壽喔
Well then, it'll be Frieren's job.
既然如此，那就交給芙莉蓮了
She will carry memories of us into the future.
她會把我們的回憶帶到未來的
Isn't that right?
不是嗎？
Sure, I don't mind.
我是無所謂啦
I see.
這樣啊
You're blessed with good friends.
你有一群很好的夥伴呢
Well then, I will have to
這樣的話，以後我就得
show Frieren my collection of handsome poses later.
讓芙莉蓮看看我的英姿全集
Can I rethink keeping you in my memory?
果然還是不要記住你比較好吧？
His collection of handsome poses was really unnecessary, though.
不過我果然不需要他的英姿全集呢
It's a waste of my memory.
根本就是浪費我的記憶容量嘛
Do you remember the face of that hero?
妳還記得那位勇者的長相嗎？
Of course, I do.
那是當然的
And his voice?
那聲音呢？
Don't underestimate me.
你可不要小看我了
I remember it all.
我全部都記得
Himmel is the reason why I started wanting to know about humans.
欣梅爾可是 讓我想要了解人類的契機啊
Just like your reason for protecting this village,
就跟你保護這個村子的契機一樣
it's important to me.
他是很重要的人
I see… The reason, huh?
這樣啊，契機嗎？
I cannot remember anymore.
老夫已經記不起來了
Neither her face, her voice, nor her gaze.
不論是妻子的臉龐、聲音或眼神
Even still,
儘管如此
I am protecting this village for something
我依舊會為了我所重視的理由
that is important to me.
在守護這個村子
Old Man Voll, you're such a jokester.
弗爾爺爺真是會說笑
By the way,
話說回來
where are you all headed to on this journey?
你們這趟旅程的目的地在哪裡？
We're headed for Aureole, "The land where souls rest."
我們要前往靈魂長眠之地
Where is that?
那個地方在哪裡？
In Ende, where the Demon King's castle is.
在恩德，也就是魔王城所在的地方
I see.
這樣啊
So you're going to defeat the Demon King, huh?
所以你們要去打倒魔王了嗎？
I can't wait for an era of peace.
要是能迎來和平的時代就好了
Old Man Voll…
弗爾爺爺
the Demon King is already…
魔王已經…
What's wrong?
怎麼了嗎？
Old Man Voll, I will carry
弗爾爺爺，我也會
your memories to the future as well.
把你的回憶帶到未來
Okay.
好
That doesn't sound so bad.
聽起來不錯呢
I'm glad I was able to see you during the last days of my life.
在人生最後的時光裡 能夠見到妳真是太好了
You said the same thing 80 years ago.
八十年前你也說過一樣的話喔
Bye, Old Man Voll. Take care.
再見了，弗爾爺爺，要保重喔
Frieren…
芙莉蓮…
My wife appeared in my dream.
我夢到妻子了
I see.
這樣啊
Maybe it's thanks to
說不定
the fact that we reminisced about the past.
是託了跟妳聊起往事的福呢
See you.
那就再見了
29 YEARS FROM THE DEATH OF HIMMEL THE HERO
（勇者欣梅爾逝世的29年後）
ROHR ROAD IN THE NORTHERN LANDS
（北方諸國，羅亞街道）
-You had a question? -I'm looking for someone.
-你在打聽什麼？ -我在找人
You remember the goal of my journey, right?
妳還記得我踏上旅途的目的吧？
Wasn't it to travel with a sexy, older lady?
不是為了 跟性感的大姐姐一起旅行嗎？
That is important too.
那個確實也很重要
But the goal of my journey is this.
不過我旅行的目的是這個
To meet my friend who embarked on a journey ten years ago.
找到十年前踏上旅途的朋友
-Oh, that's right. -Huh?
-說起來是有這麼一回事呢 -咦？
A photo, huh? That's pretty rare.
是照片耶，還真少見
We had one taken
很久以前
by a mage who came to our village long time ago.
村裡來了一個魔法使，這是他拍的
Do you have any leads?
那你有線索了嗎？
We've been taking the main roads
我們一直沿著
that go through the northern lands,
北方諸國的主幹道走
so I've already met some eyewitnesses.
已經遇到幾個見過他的人了
It should be fine to keep going north.
應該繼續往北走就好了
It was ten years ago, right? How are there still eyewitnesses?
那是十年前的事了吧 怎麼還會有見過他的人？
He has a unique name, after all.
畢竟他的名字很特別
It leaves an impression.
會讓人印象深刻
What's his name?
他叫什麼名字？
Gorilla Warrior.
大猩猩戰士
Right…
這樣喔
And his real name?
那真名呢？
-Real name? -Were you really best friends?
-真名？ -你們真的是摯友？
Everyone in the village used to always
以前村裡的人都習慣叫他
call him Gorilla Warrior.
“大猩猩戰士”
More like, he forced everyone to call him that.
或者更該說是他要大家這麼叫他的
How did that come to be?
這是什麼情況啊？
By the way, I was called Goatee Priest.
對了，我的話叫做“山羊鬍僧侶”
Nobody asked.
沒有人問你
Were you called that even before you grew a goatee?
所以你還沒留鬍子之前 就有人這麼叫你了？
Are we really going to expand on this topic?
真的要繼續聊這個話題嗎？
In any case,
不管怎樣
as long as you remember "Gorilla Warrior" that's fine.
只要記得大猩猩戰士 這個名字就可以了
He will always introduce himself that way.
反正那傢伙一定會這樣介紹自己
-What a weird guy. -Yeah.
-真是個怪胎 -是啊
He's a weird guy.
他真是個怪胎
Once we pass this giant canyon and walk for about a week,
穿過這個大峽谷，再走上一星期左右
we'll finally reach Äußerst, the city of magic.
就可以抵達魔法之都歐伊沙斯特了
This was a really long trip…
真的是很漫長的旅途呢
Why are you looking at me?
看我幹什麼？
I didn't do anything wrong this time.
這次我可什麼都沒做喔
Before that, can we stop by this village?
話說，能不能順路去那個村子走走？
The road branches off into multiple directions here.
這條路上有很多這樣的分岔路
That's fine. We need to rest as well.
好啊，正好我們也需要休息一下
Hey,
借問一下
did someone named Gorilla come by here ten years ago?
十年前有沒有個 自稱是“大猩猩”的人經過這裡？
What a crazy thing to ask…
好厲害的問法
Oh, you mean Gorilla Warrior!
你是說大猩猩戰士吧！
He actually knows?
他還真的知道啊？
It left such a strong impression, I remember it well.
因為印象太深刻了 所以想忘也忘不了呢
He defeated a monster that appeared near the village.
他打敗了村子附近出現的魔物
Do you know which way he went after that?
你知道在那之後他去了哪裡嗎？
Let me think…
我想想喔…
Master Gorilla
大猩猩大人
was friends with the stubborn old woman who lives up on the hill,
跟住在山坡上那位死老太婆是好朋友
so try asking her.
可以去問她看看
Stubborn old woman? That's another unique nickname.
死老太婆？又是一個奇特的稱號
I am stubborn by nature.
我天生就很頑固
So I can't give you information so easily.
所以不會輕易告訴你們情報
She admits that she's stubborn?
自己都承認自己很頑固？
What can we do?
那我們要怎麼做？
I will have you fulfill a few requests for me.
你們替我去辦幾件事吧
First, deliver this letter to Nagel, the blacksmith
先把這封信送給鐵匠納格爾
who lives in the next town over.
他就住在隔壁的小鎮
I'm like an errand boy.
簡直就像是跑腿的嘛
This reminds me of my journey with Himmel.
這讓我想起了 跟欣梅爾一起旅行的時光了
You did these kinds of things too?
你們當時也跑過腿嗎？
We would help others by running errands almost every day.
我們幾乎每天都會幫別人跑腿
Those kinds of errands
這些跑腿的差事
tend to turn into more troublesome searches and monster exterminations.
最後都會演變成更麻煩的尋找物品 或是要跟魔物戰鬥什麼的
Don't say that or it might happen.
不要說這種觸霉頭的話
Anyway, let's do our best so she opens up her heart to us.
總之，我們就盡力 讓婆婆對我們敞開心扉吧
This old woman isn't opening her heart at all.
這位老婆婆的心扉 完全沒有要打開的意思
She lives up to her name, "stubborn old woman."
“死老太婆”果然人如其名
Sorry…
抱歉啊
If Himmel or Heiter were here, she would've opened up in half a day.
如果有欣梅爾或海塔在的話 應該半天就能打開她的心扉了
After all, nobody in this party has people skills.
畢竟我們的隊伍裡 沒有人擅長討人歡心啊
Here.
拿去
Huh?
幹嘛？
It's the last one.
這是最後一個了
Polish the statue of heroes in the canyon.
把峽谷裡的英雄雕像清理一下
Follow me. I will show you the way.
跟我來，我來帶路
What's this "statue of heroes"?
什麼英雄雕像？
It's a stone statue of heroes who are said to have
是座石像，據說是很久以前
saved the world long ago.
拯救了全世界的英雄
That's all I know about it.
我知道的就這麼多了
They're forgotten heroes whose names we don't even know.
名字沒有人知道，被遺忘的英雄
The villagers have been maintaining it for generations.
由這裡的村民世世代代維護著
Forgotten heroes, huh?
被遺忘的英雄嗎？
By the way, you are Goatee Priest, aren't you?
話說回來，你就是山羊鬍僧侶吧？
Huh?
咦？
How do you know?
妳怎麼會知道？
We're here.
到了
A priest and a warrior?
僧侶跟戰士？
It looks pretty old.
看起來很老舊了
It kind of looks like Master Sein and Master Gorilla.
怎麼感覺有點像 贊恩大人跟大猩猩大人？
More like, that warrior looks so familiar.
說起來，這個戰士看起來很眼熟…
-It's Kraft. -Oh?
-是克拉福特 -哦？
-You're right! -It looks exactly like him.
-真的耶！ -看起來就跟他一模一樣
Well then, let's get started.
那麼趕緊工作吧
-Sein? -I see.
-贊恩？ -原來如此
So his name is Kraft, huh?
所以這個人就叫做克拉福特嗎？
-What about this one? -I don't know.
-那這邊這個呢？ -這個我也不知道
I see…
這樣啊…
What's this statue?
這座石像是怎麼回事？
Don't they look exactly like us?
跟我們簡直一模一樣吧？
According to the village chief, they are heroes from a long, long time ago.
村長說過 這兩位是遠古時代的大英雄
But nobody even remembers their names.
但是沒有半個人記得他們的名字
We won't become like them.
我們才不會變得跟他們一樣
I'd hate to be forgotten.
我討厭被人遺忘
We'll become heroes
我們要成為像勇者欣梅爾那樣
that nobody can forget, like Himmel the Hero.
讓人永遠銘記於心的英雄
No matter how great of a hero you are, you will be forgotten one day.
不管是多偉大的英雄 總有一天會被人遺忘
Even Himmel the Hero, who defeated the Demon King,
就算是打倒魔王的勇者欣梅爾
is no exception.
也是不例外
That makes sense. Of course, it's not possible.
說得也是，果然不可能被人永遠記住
Will I turn out like this if I work out too?
如果我認真鍛鍊的話 會變得像他一樣嗎？
Gorilla Warrior!
大猩猩戰士！
That will be my name from today!
從今以後我就叫這個名字！
Why?
為什麼？
If I want to become an unforgettable hero,
如果要成為不被遺忘的英雄
my name should leave an impression.
那名字就得讓人印象深刻才行
That is true.
確實如此呢
Then you would be Goatee Priest.
那你就會是山羊鬍僧侶了吧
That's great!
很好啊！
I'm sure you will look good in a goatee.
我敢說山羊鬍一定很適合你
Finally, it's done…
總算清完了
That was a lot of work.
有夠累人
If only it was a bronze statue, we could've used magic.
如果是銅像的話 就可以用魔法清理了
I asked Gorilla to do the same thing,
我要求大猩猩做過一樣的事
but he couldn't do it this well.
但那傢伙就沒辦法清理得這麼乾淨
Fighting is his only strong suit.
那傢伙的優點就只有會戰鬥而已
But his name did indeed, leave a strong impression.
不過他的名字確實叫人印象深刻呢
Gorilla always talked about you.
大猩猩總是提到你
He said that the two of you will become heroes whose names
他說你們會一起成為
will be engraved in history forever.
把名字永遠刻在歷史上的英雄
Did you find out where Gorilla went?
知道大猩猩的去向了嗎？
Tür.
提亞
It's a trade city in the northern lands.
那是北方諸國的貿易都市
NORTHEM LANDS - TÜR
（北方諸國，提亞）
It's farther east from here.
要從這裡往東邊走吧
In the opposite direction from Äußerst.
跟歐伊沙斯特是反方向呢
Yeah.
是啊
What should I do…
該怎麼辦呢？
Come into
輪流
-theroom next door, one at a time. -You should rest.
-到隔壁的房間來 -應該要好好休息
-Mediating is a priest's job. -The medicine is ready.
-調解是僧侶的工作 -藥已經做好了
It's embarrassing.
很難為情啊
I'm so thoughtful and handsome, aren't I?
懂得體貼別人的我很帥氣吧？
"Take Care."
《那就多保重了》
Subtitle translation by: Kiko Morita
字幕翻譯：洪貞韻